<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[technicall]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-24T13:17:25-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Isaac Dontje Lindell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Something Out Of Nothing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/24/creating-something-out-of-nothing/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T12:40:44-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/24/creating-something-out-of-nothing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, we visited Coloft, a co-working space in Santa Monica. We met with one of the cofounders of Coloft, Avesta Rasouli. Avesta is a serial entrepreneur who had some really interesting thoughts and advice on startups, especially in Silicon Valley. I&rsquo;m just going to talk about of few of the points he made that stood out at me, in no particular order.</p>

<h3>Picking a partner</h3>

<p>Avesta really stressed the importance of picking (a) partner(s) who have/has complementary skill sets. If you&rsquo;re really good at coding, it&rsquo;s pretty important to have someone who can manage a business and make sales (this really echoes the concept of the &ldquo;4 hats of entrepreneurship&rdquo; that we heard from the guys at PerCognate).</p>

<p>According to Avestar, once you have people with complementary skill sets to start a venture with, you have to be willing to stay out of each other&rsquo;s business. You&rsquo;ve got to be willing to trust that the other person (who has skills you don&rsquo;t) knows what their doing. If you try to micromanage everything, the venture is probably going to fail.</p>

<h3>Solve other people&rsquo;s problems, not yours</h3>

<p>This one was interesting for me: Avestar said that it&rsquo;s often important to resist the urge to start something that solves your problems. You need to make sure their&rsquo;s a market for what you&rsquo;re doing (which involves, obviously, talking to people). If you talk to four people, and three of them have the same problem, that might be a good market to go after. If you have a problem you can solve with a product, don&rsquo;t spend a ton of time assuming that other&rsquo;s have that problem: you have to make sure you aren&rsquo;t wasting your time.</p>

<p>I think this is one that I could struggle with. I&rsquo;m obviously not going out and starting a business right now, but when I start projects, they&rsquo;re generally aimed to solve a need I have &ndash; most of what I do wouldn&rsquo;t be very useful to other people.</p>

<h3>Ideas don&rsquo;t mean shit</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;ve heard this one a number of times: ideas are a dime a dozen. Everyone has good ideas. It&rsquo;s the execution that takes skill and effort. On a related note, Avestar was pretty dismissive of non-disclosure agreements. He won&rsquo;t sign them in exchange for listening to an idea, and he said that most people in Silicon Valley won&rsquo;t either. This connects to the fact that ideas are cheap: if you have a good idea, telling everyone probably won&rsquo;t make a difference. In fact, someone has already probably had your idea, but wouldn&rsquo;t or couldn&rsquo;t execute it. That&rsquo;s what distinguishes an entrepreneur.</p>

<h3>The loudest people are often not the smartest</h3>

<p>This is pretty self-explanatory. It&rsquo;s easy to get caught up in how many people follow you on Twitter, or to talk up your ideas and convince people. But the smartest people are the ones who don&rsquo;t waste time with stuff like that: they&rsquo;re actually out building stuff.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sportvision and Fenwick &amp; West]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/22/sportvision-and-fenwick-and-west/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-22T18:22:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/22/sportvision-and-fenwick-and-west</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;ve been on a train now for about nine hours, so you can probably imagine that I&rsquo;m about ready to be done. We should be arriving in Santa Monica in a few hours.</p>

<p>Yesterday was our last day in Menlo Park/Mountain View, and we visited two companies.</p>

<p>The first was Sportvision. Sportvision is one of those companies that you&rsquo;ve probably never heard of, but you&rsquo;ve definitely seen their work. Their technology is responsible for all kinds of &ldquo;virtual reality&rdquo; images on sports broadcast. Their most famous product is the yellow &ldquo;first and ten&rdquo; line that you see superimposed on the field during pro and college football games. They also do graphics and visualizations for hockey, baseball, soccer, basketball, auto racing, and even sometimes skiing. Their biggest area of growth, however, is in data collection. They are putting sensors on players or using cameras to track players, and packaging that data in various different ways to sell to various clients. (The simplest client would be a football team buying the movement and position data for all their players during a game so they can later go back and replay and analyze every play.)</p>

<p>Technologically, this was one of the most sophisticated business we&rsquo;ve seen. All of their work is based on computer vision and motion tracking, so most of their engineers aren&rsquo;t just computer scientists &ndash; they have to have tons of physics and math.</p>

<p>One of the coolest things we saw was a piece of software that can track a baseball (moving at 80-90MPH), and based on it&rsquo;s trajectory, calculate it&rsquo;s spin rate. This is <em>not</em> for the faint at heart.</p>

<p>Even the simple &ldquo;first and ten&rdquo; line isn&rsquo;t nearly as simple as it seems: how do you teach a computer to superimpose the line <em>on</em> the field but <em>below</em> any people or objects on the field? How do you automatically compensate for changing lighting conditions and variable field colors?</p>

<p>We got a great introduction to their business and technology from Michael King, who introduced himself as their director of football, but obviously has a pretty comprehensive view of the whole company.</p>

<p>The other visit we made was to the law firm Fenwick &amp; West, in downtown Mountain View. F &amp; W is a fairly large law firm, but we were meeting with specifically the patent litigation team. They have a ton of large clients, including Twitter, Amazon, and Google.</p>

<p>We had a chance to talk with five lawyers from the patent litigation team, who gave us an extremely well prepared introduction to the basics of patent law, and especially to the problems around patent trolls (TODO add link).</p>

<p>The problems with patent trolls have been well documented, so I won&rsquo;t spend a ton of time talking about them, but I did want to highlight what I thought was the most interesting point made by the F &amp; W team.</p>

<p>The most common proposal for eliminating the problem of patent trolls involves legislation that bans so-called &ldquo;non-practicing entities&rdquo; from owning or legislating based on patents. NPEs are companies who own patents but aren&rsquo;t involved in a business. Obviously, this describes patent trolls: they exist only to purchase patents and sue other companies based on those patents. They don&rsquo;t provide any other product or service.</p>

<p>The problem with such proposed legislation is that, technically, universities are non-practicing entities as well. Nobody wants to argue that what research universities are doing isn&rsquo;t valuable and shouldn&rsquo;t be afforded patent protection. How do you draw the line, though? It&rsquo;s difficult or impossible to draw the line in such a way that it excludes patent trolls while still fairly including universities and other non-profit but still patent-producing institutions.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m certainly not a lawyer, and I have no idea where to draw the line, but it was incredibly interesting to hear about some of the issues directly from lawyers who have to deal with patent trolls every day!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using GVM (Go version manager) To Install Golang]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/19/using-gvm-go-version-manager-to-install-golang/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T10:17:59-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/19/using-gvm-go-version-manager-to-install-golang</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m starting a project in Go. The first step was obviously to install Go, but after a half hour wrestling with an old and broken installation and a out-of-date PPA, I got fed up.</p>

<p>Then I found <a href="https://github.com/moovweb/gvm">gvm</a>. If you&rsquo;re familiar with rvm for Ruby, I think you&rsquo;re going to like gvm.</p>

<p>Setup on Ubuntu is pretty simple:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>bash &lt; &lt;<span class="o">(</span>curl -s https://raw.github.com/moovweb/gvm/master/binscripts/gvm-installer<span class="o">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then you&rsquo;ll need to restart your terminal.</p>

<p>Since the install script seems to assume you&rsquo;re using bash, if you&rsquo;re using a shell other than bash, you&rsquo;ll need to add this to your config file (e.g .zshrc, etc):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>[[ -s "$HOME/.gvm/scripts/gvm" ]] && source "$HOME/.gvm/scripts/gvm"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>In my case, I wanted the latest version of Go (1.2 as of this writing), so I ran:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>gvm install go1.2
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>gvm use go1.2 --default
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The <code>--default</code> flag sets that particular version of go as the default when you open a new terminal session.</p>

<p>It was fun to see that gvm was written by the devs at <a href="http://www.moovweb.com/">MoovWeb</a>. When I visited them a few days ago I was interested that they were using Go for their backend &ndash; clearly they&rsquo;re pretty invested!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When "Just Trust Us" Isn't Good Enough]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/when-just-trust-us-isnt-good-enough/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T17:16:29-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/when-just-trust-us-isnt-good-enough</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I originally wrote this paper for an interdisciplinary Ethics and Technology course, during the fall of 2013.</em></p>

<p>Net neutrality is a term frequently encountered when discussing access to information on the Internet. While it is generally intended to refer to a guarantee of certain qualities of access to the global Internet, it has been specifically defined in many different ways. I intend to ethically analyze the various aspects of net neutrality, including several common definitions. I will contend that a definition of net neutrality that allows for network traffic prioritization and shaping is ethical, but only for the purposes of managing and improving the network. Non-net neutrality is unethical if it is done for financial gain (e.g. “pay extra for the premium sites package”), if it is not transparent to the end user, or is done to discriminate against a particular class of users.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Before any critical and ethical analysis of net neutrality can be made, we must first understand what the term “net neutrality” means. There are a number of definitions in wide use, each with a slightly different point of view as to what does and does not constitute net neutrality. We will briefly explore several of these before arriving at a definition that will be used in the remainder of this analysis.</p>

<p>The term net neutrality was first used by Tim Wu<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, Professor of Law at Columbia University. The most basic definition of net neutrality adopted by Wu is as a principle applicable to network design:</p>

<blockquote><p>A maximally useful public information network aspires to treat all content, sites, and platforms equally (Wu, 2003).</p></blockquote>


<p>To support this definition, Wu describes, as an example of a neutral network, the public electricity grid. The electricity grid is designed to be end-use agnostic, allowing any device to utilize it. The utility company responsible for designing and maintaining the grid does not design the network for any particular use or device, but rather operates it on the principle of neutral, general purpose use. (The electrical network is obviously not an “information network,” but the metaphor is still useful to clarify Wu&rsquo;s definition.)</p>

<p>Another definition, more specific to Internet computer networks, is put forth by Krämer <em>et al</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> in “Net Neutrality Progress”:</p>

<blockquote><p>Net neutrality prohibits Internet service providers from speeding up, slowing down or blocking Internet traffic based on its source, ownership or destination (Krämer et al).</p></blockquote>


<p>It is important to note here the differences between this definition, referred to as “strict network neutrality”, and the general definition adopted by Wu. The definition used in Krämer <em>et al</em> allows for differing treatment of broad categories of Internet traffic in order to manage various forms of content with different requirements (e.g. low latency requirements for Internet voice communication versus the relative insensitivity to latency exhibited by peer-to-peer download systems). Wu&rsquo;s definition of a maximally useful public information network does not allow for such discrimination, even when discrimination is useful as a tool to improve the quality of service to the majority of users of a network without significantly reducing the quality of service provided to the minority. I will explore the use of non-net neutrality as a tool to improve the quality of the network later in this paper.</p>

<p>A third, even more specific, definition of net neutrality is provided by Hahn <em>et al</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> in “The Economics of Net Neutrality.” They claim that net neutrality means that:</p>

<blockquote><p>Broadband service providers charge consumers only once for Internet access, do not favor one content provider over another, and do not charge content providers for sending information over broadband lines to end users (Hahn et al).</p></blockquote>


<p>The model where service providers do charge content providers for sending information to end users is referred to by Krämer <em>et al</em> as the “termination fee model.” This model is of interest because of its potential to adversely affect certain types of services. For example, providers of streaming video, by the nature of their product, generate much more network traffic than providers of textual content. This does not imply that one type of content is intrinsically better or more useful, but under a termination fee model, content providers whose service requires more network traffic may have to pay significantly more to reach consumers.</p>

<p>The remainder of this analysis will use the definition of net neutrality given by Krämer <em>et al</em>, with the addendum that any practices that cause anything but strict and total equality in the treatment of network traffic must be transparently and effectively communicated to the consumers affected. From an ethical perspective, this is the most defensible of the three definitions given above.  We will explore in greater depth the issues inherent in the definitions of network neutrality provided by Tim Wu and Hahn <em>et al</em>, as well as outline why the principle of net neutrality as defined in Krämer <em>et al</em> is an important concept to uphold when setting policy and designing legislation.</p>

<p>To ethically analyze the issue of net neutrality, it is first useful to assert that the Internet as a resource for obtaining, creating, and sharing information is a service that can have an enormously positive effect on humanity. The Internet was created from a vision of an idealized, decentralized, democratic inter-network of computers. It has increasingly become a tool to enfranchise people. On the Internet, in theory, any person has the tools needed to express their view. Small businesses can compete on a level playing field with entrenched monopolies. People in countries with oppressive social and political policies can use the Internet to anonymously advocate for positive change. However, these benefits can only be retained and expanded if the principles of non-discrimination given by net neutrality can be upheld.</p>

<p>The definition of net neutrality adopted above does not claim that all network traffic must be treated with total equality. In fact, such a policy would be inimical to the goal of providing everyone with an equal opportunity to benefit from the Internet. The issue is primarily technical. Different categories of network traffic have different requirements, and place different levels of demand on the network of the service provider. As alluded to above, real-time voice communication over the Internet (voice over Internet Protocol, or VoIP) is relatively bandwidth unintensive. However, VoIP communication is very strongly dependent on low levels of latency (the speed at which one single piece of data can travel from the source to the destination). On the other hand, peer-to-peer (P2P) file sharing protocols are extremely bandwidth intensive, while being essentially unaffected by high levels of latency. If a principle of strict traffic equality is adhered to, a user attempting to utilize VoIP will be harmed by a user utilizing peer-to-peer file sharing on the network. This is contrary to the principle of fair and equal access: the VoIP user is unfairly penalized, while the P2P user gains no benefit.</p>

<p>In this situation, a policy that prioritizes VoIP traffic over traffic generated by the P2P user is the correct option. The amount of bandwidth used by the prioritized VoIP user is minimally impacts the experience of  the P2P user, while dramatically increasing the experience of that VoIP user. The end result is that both users are granted fair and useful access to the network.</p>

<p>Service providers that adopt such measures, however, must be carefully monitored to ensure that such traffic management is done strictly to ensure the equality of all types of network communication. The temptation in a market where service providers are profit-driven is that competitive service providers will use traffic shaping and prioritization for financial gain, at the expense of consumers. We have already encountered one of these scenarios in the so-called termination fee model, where content providers may be unfairly discriminated against due to the nature of their content&rsquo;s delivery requirements.</p>

<p>Another possible scenario inimical to the interests of Internet users is that of the “cable television” model. In this situation, service providers may begin offering consumers predetermined packages of Internet content access. For example, a service provider may offer a “Basic Internet” package, allowing users access to a handful of popular, preselected sites. Access to other sites is only granted if the user pays for the “Premium Internet” package. This scenario is problematic in that it disenfranchises content producers who are not among the list of preselected, popular Internet content providers.</p>

<p>Issues related to deliberate discrimination and suppression of speech must also be carefully watched for. Under the guise of network traffic management, it is easy to envision a scenario where a service provider unfairly degrades or even blocks content that is distasteful to its controlling interests, whether that distaste arises from political, moral, or financial reasons. While there may be no legal protection for unwanted speech on private networks in this country, such discrimination is contrary to the ethical ideals of the Internet, and should be avoided in order to promote the benefits of ubiquitous inter-networking for everyone.</p>

<p>The final component of an ethical application of net neutrality is that any action taken by a service provider beyond strict, unmanaged equality of all network traffic must be transparently and effectively communicated to any users affected. It is difficult to accept that a service provider is protecting the interests of the network users if traffic is manipulated in secrecy. Such concerns are not merely theoretical. In 2007, it was revealed that Comcast, a large Internet service provider, was routinely throttling traffic using the BitTorrent peer-to-peer file sharing protocol (Wired, 2008)<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. The throttling was done secretly, and was targeted at a specific application of the Internet. It continues to remain unclear whether that traffic shaping was done for the purpose of improving the experience of all users of the network, or whether there was another motivation. It is certainly possible that Comcast was protecting the interests of users who may have been adversely affected by BitTorrent traffic. However, Comcast is also a large provider to cable television services, which are often seen to be in competition with P2P sources of media. Comcast&rsquo;s deliberate secrecy over the practice of throttling such traffic causes significant suspicion of ulterior motives.</p>

<p>Clearly, net neutrality is a complex issue with many ethical facets. I have argued an ethical definition of net neutrality that attempts to level the playing field for all users of the Internet, a definition that disallows discrimination based on source, destination, and owner. Additionally, for a policy of network traffic management to be ethically sound, any actions taken by the service provider must be open and transparent to any user affected by such actions. To maintain an open, fair, and beneficial Internet any actions taken by service providers that fail to meet these criteria should be viewed with immediate suspicion.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Wu, Tim. &ldquo;Network Neutrality FAQ.&rdquo; Network Neutrality FAQ. N.p., n.d. Web. 03 Dec. 2013. <a href="http://timwu.org/network_neutrality.html">http://timwu.org/network_neutrality.html</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Kraemer, Jan and Wiewiorra, Lukas and Weinhardt, Christof, Net Neutrality: A Progress Report (October 24, 2013). Telecommunications Policy 37(9). 794–813.. Available at SSRN: <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=2344623">http://ssrn.com/abstract=2344623</a> or <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2344623">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2344623</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Hahn, Robert W. and Wallsten, Scott, The Economics of Net Neutrality (April 2006). AEI-Brookings Joint Center Working Paper No. RP06-13. Available at SSRN: <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=943757">http://ssrn.com/abstract=943757</a> or <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.94375">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.94375</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Kravets, David. &ldquo;Comcast Discloses Throttling Practices — BitTorrent Targeted.&#8221;Wired.com. Conde Nast Digital, 19 Sept. 2008. Web. 03 Dec. 2013. <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2008/09/comcast-disclos/">http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2008/09/comcast-disclos/</a>.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assimilation into the GooglePlex]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/assimilation-into-the-googleplex/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T09:26:02-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/assimilation-into-the-googleplex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, we visited Google headquarters, in Mountain View, California. It was certainly an impressive experience, but I was left with some mixed feelings about the experience.</p>

<p>First of all, Google is obviously doing some really cool stuff. My computer and Internet experience would be very different without Google. I use Gmail, Calendar, Maps, Search, Chrome, and other products every day. Large parts of the Internet are financed by Google-served ads.</p>

<p>Google also has the deep pockets and corporate will to perform groundbreaking research. Their self-driving car is incredible, and Google Glass is pretty revolutionary (whatever you think about the benefit to humanity).</p>

<p>On the other hand, I found myself fairly uncomfortable at many points during our visit yesterday. One of the people we met was Craig Cornelius, a former Luther alumna who works on the internationalization team (i18n) at Google. One of the first things Craig said when he starting talking about Google was, &ldquo;how much do you pay Google to use our services?&rdquo; It&rsquo;s a fairly innocuous question, but he clearly expected us to answer that we paid nothing.</p>

<p>When someone said that we paid with our personal information, he sort of acknowledged the point, but then immediately moved on to convincing us that because we don&rsquo;t &ldquo;cut Google a check,&rdquo; we really aren&rsquo;t paying anything. That unwillingness to acknowledge Google&rsquo;s core money-maker (our data) leaves a bad taste in my mouth.</p>

<p>I give them that data willingly, in exchange for some very useful services and products. But if Craig&rsquo;s perspective is common at Google, I have to feel like they&rsquo;re simply trying to forget (or convince the rest of us to forget) that we <em>are</em> paying them.</p>

<p>I did enjoying seeing the campus with Charles Banta (a recent Luther grad, and someone I&rsquo;ve worked with at the Luther Tech Help Desk), and getting to see some of the perks that Googlers get. Google clearly views time that employees are not on campus as wasted time. And when you can eat, drink, sleep, get a haircut, get your car repaired, do your laundry, see a doctor, and work out on campus, what&rsquo;s the point of going home?</p>

<p>Again, it would be fun to work at Google, and I know that Charles is really enjoying it. But I can&rsquo;t help but think that your life would quickly become Google-centric. It&rsquo;s one thing to love your job and want to work a lot (a situation I hope to find myself in when I enter the job market), but the word &ldquo;assimilation&rdquo; kept popping in to my head during the entire visit. (For a fictional take on this, I highly recommend reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18302455-the-circle">The Circle</a> by Dave Eggers. Just replace &ldquo;The Circle&rdquo; with &ldquo;Google&rdquo; and you&rsquo;ll have a good idea how I felt visting Google.)</p>

<p>Two of the technical talks we heard, however, were fantastic. Craig Cornelius gave a lecture on the challenges of internationalization of Google products. It didn&rsquo;t sound that interesting at first, but his team has to solve so incredibly difficult projects. How you design projects so that they work equally well with left-to-right AND right-to-left languages? How do you handle keyboard input in a language that has thousands of &ldquo;letters&rdquo;? How do you deal with one of the hundreds of ways a single date and time can be expressed?</p>

<p>We also had a chance to hear a little bit from Brian, an engineer on Google&rsquo;s self-driving car team (unfortunately, I didn&rsquo;t manage to catch his last name). We didn&rsquo;t have a chance to get as technical as I would have liked due to time issues, but he had a great introduction to the technology behind the &ldquo;perception suite&rdquo; that&rsquo;s used to make the car &ldquo;see&rdquo;, and some interesting scenarios for possible societal changes that might be caused by the introduction of autonomous cars.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[That's not how you Constitution, Mr. Obama]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/17/thats-not-how-you-constitution/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-17T18:09:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/17/thats-not-how-you-constitution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>President Obama gave a speech today. The topic was the NSA; he was addressing the recommendations given by the panel of experts he appointed to review the actions taken by the spy agency.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m fairly disappointed in Obama&rsquo;s response. He failed to address or paid only lip service to some pretty important issues.</p>

<h3>Advocate for the defense in the FISA court</h3>

<p>One issue of potential constitutional significance is that cases heard in the secret FISA court are completely one sided: the judges hear only the government&rsquo;s side. The review panel recommended that an advocate be appointed to argue against the government (for the defendants who don&rsquo;t even know that they&rsquo;re being considered for surveillance).</p>

<p>In his speech today, President Obama said that he will create a &ldquo;panel of advocates&rdquo; to represent privacy concerns in significant cases.</p>

<p>From The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote><p>A senior official said the advocates would be called on only in cases presenting novel and important privacy law issues. The panel would apparently not have the authority to monitor the court’s caseload and independently decide when a case warranted its presence.</p><footer><strong>The New York Times</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/01/17/us/nsa-changes-graphic.html'>www.nytimes.com/interactive/01/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>So basically, the &ldquo;advocate panel&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t have any power whatsoever. How can the right to counsel be respected if no one has the power to argue against the government? Who decides if a case &ldquo;[presents] novel and important privacy law issues&rdquo;? If the FISA court or the prosecution (i.e. the government/NSA) is responsible for make such a determination, that&rsquo;s hardly better than not having an advocate panel at all!</p>

<h3>Secrecy of National Security Letters</h3>

<p>The other disappointment for me was President Obama&rsquo;s failure to implement the requirement that a judge sign off before a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_security_letter">national security letter</a> (NSL) can be served. He did change the policy on the mandatory gag orders that stop recipients of NSLs from discussing them or even mentioning that they&rsquo;d received one. The gag orders will now have a fixed expiration date. It&rsquo;s not perfect: he didn&rsquo;t say how long that fixed expiration time period will be (if it&rsquo;s longer than a few months, what&rsquo;s the point?) and the weasel words, &ldquo;in most cases,&rdquo; make me uncomfortable.</p>

<p>There are a lot of other specific recommendations by the review panel that I think Mr. Obama stopped short of adequately addressing. I&rsquo;d recommend reading the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/01/17/us/nsa-changes-graphic.html">NYTimes</a> piece &ndash; it does a great job of breaking down his response to each of the recommendations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Here's Your Morning Dose of Absurdity]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/17/heres-your-morning-dose-of-absurdity/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-17T09:29:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/17/heres-your-morning-dose-of-absurdity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s really no other word for this than absurd. Bruce Schneier was asked to <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2014/01/today_i_briefed.html">brief six members of Congress yesterday</a> on the NSA&rsquo;s activities&hellip;because the NSA won&rsquo;t tell Congress what they&rsquo;re doing. Really?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Future of Software: Venture Capitalists vs. Scientists]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/16/hummer-winblad-and-phillip-alvelda/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T23:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/16/hummer-winblad-and-phillip-alvelda</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was our last day here in San Francisco. Tomorrow morning, we&rsquo;re getting on a shuttle down to Palo Alto/Mountain View and the GooglePlex!</p>

<p>This morning, we met with Ann Winblad, of Hummer Winblad Venture Partners. (Ann&rsquo;s VC firm was one of the early funders of Brad&rsquo;s startup, NetPerceptions). Ann is an incredibly engaging speaker, and she gave us a great intro to the world of venture capital, and a lot of description of where she thinks the world of commercial software development is going.</p>

<p>One of Ann&rsquo;s main points is that software development is no longer a task where an isolated startup or other company will write a product from the ground up. Instead, software development comes down to connecting existing components together, leveraging existing corpora of data or databases of prepackaged software components (e.g. Maven).</p>

<p>I found myself thinking about this a lot, and I&rsquo;m still not sure if I totally agree. It&rsquo;s very true that it&rsquo;s easy to build cool pieces of software simply by leveraging other existing software. For example, I&rsquo;m working on a web application that&rsquo;s a prettier, friendlier front end to the Calibre ebook management software. I&rsquo;m (obviously) using the interface exposed by Calibre to get book metadata. I&rsquo;m using Bootstrap to lay out the interface (a designer I am not!). I&rsquo;m using a framework called Angular.js to handle displaying data and updating it easily.</p>

<p>On the other hand, doing this still requires a fair amount of &ldquo;glue&rdquo; code. I have to design a user flow. I have to make sure the right data is shown at the right time. Even with Bootstrap, I have to make at least some effort to make sure it looks decent.</p>

<p>Another perspective on this came from Phillip Alvelda, a serial entrepreneur and scientist, whom we also met with today. Phillip&rsquo;s counterpoint when I mentioned what Ann had talked about was that I should take anything said by a venture capitalist with a grain of salt. They aim to find investments that are low risk and have a very high potential payoff. Designing software that builds on already existing software takes less time and programmer skill (i.e. lower risk) and consequently has a better chance of &ldquo;getting big.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Phillip&rsquo;s point is that while the type of development Ann favored is a quick way to make money, it&rsquo;s not a good way to truly innovate. Things that require scientific research, or hardware investment, or both, are risky and expensive. While they often have a chance at a huge payoff, venture capitalists are very hesitant to fund such ventures. (Phillip gave the specific example of Elon Musk&rsquo;s now-abandoned hyperloop idea: it had the potential to be extremely innovative, but was expensive and very risky).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also taking what Phillip said about VCs (and Ann Winblad specifically) with a small grain of salt: he mentioned that he&rsquo;s asked Hummer Winblad for investment for three different ventures, and has been turned down all three times&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bizo, MoovWeb, and Sara Ellefsen]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/15/bizo/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T19:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/15/bizo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was a really long day! We visited three groups, all doing very different things.</p>

<p>This morning, we met with a company called Bizo. Bizo does B2B (business to business) Internet marketing. Their customers are other businesses who want to run advertising campaigns on the Internet. They had some interesting perspectives on their business, which is in many ways bigger than a startup but still a pretty small company, but the most interesting part of the conversation for me was in the interview and career advice they had near the end of our visit.</p>

<p>They emphasized that when they interview people, one of their primary concerns (beyond a minimum technical bar) is that the candidate matches their culture. I heard over and over, &ldquo;is this [candidate] someone I would enjoy working with?&rdquo; I couldn&rsquo;t help but draw comparisons to the way that Matt at VMWare talked about hiring. He was much more concerned about technical ability and problem solving; he said several times that he wanted to work with &ldquo;the smartest people in the world.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Brad (our professor) had an interesting perspective on that: the people at Bizo are doing interesting things, but they aren&rsquo;t doing revolutionary or innovative computer science. They&rsquo;re just &ldquo;pushing bits around&rdquo;. On the other hand, VMWare is obviously tackling some very difficult engineering problems. The ablilty of the candidate is much more important than their &ldquo;culture fit.&rdquo;</p>

<p>We met with some developers from a company called MoovWeb for lunch. MoovWeb&rsquo;s service is one that allows businesses that have an existing complicated desktop web site to convert it to a mobile-friendly version with much less effort than simply re-writing the whole site. It was fun to get a chance to have some informal and in-depth technical discussions with the developers. They&rsquo;re doing some cool stuff with dynamically regenerating sites using a server side architecture (written in Go, no less!)</p>

<p>The last meeting of the day was with a personal finance planner, Sara Ellefsen. Sara works with mostly individuals and families to help them plan and manage their investment portfolio. As a broke college student, it&rsquo;s difficult for me to think about investing and financial planning, but she had some really good advice for how to approach saving and investing, and it was intriguing to see her approach to risk management.</p>

<p>Sara is certainly a (successful) entrepreneur, but of a very different philosophy than many of the startups we&rsquo;ve been meeting with. She doesn&rsquo;t have any employees, and isn&rsquo;t particularly interested in expanding. She likes what she does, and doesn&rsquo;t have grand visions of making millions and starting a global empire.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pinterest and Strava]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/14/pinterest-and-strava/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T20:59:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/14/pinterest-and-strava</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, day 9, we visited Pinterest and Strava.</p>

<p>The first visit was to the Pinterest headquarters in the Soma neighborhood of San Francisco. (If you aren&rsquo;t familiar with Pinterest, it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;social pinning&rdquo; site where users can pin pictures, links, and notes about stuff that interests them on virtual bulletin boards.)</p>

<p>We had a chance to meet with John and Dan, two data scientists at Pinterest. As data scientists, they&rsquo;re responsible for analyzing metrics related to the service that Pinterest provides, and making sure that issues are resolved. On a technical basis, that means using things like the R programming language, the Hadoop database engine, and various other analytic tools to measure metrics from user engagement to site reliability to demographic information.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting challenges that Pinterest is facing is how to expand its user base from their historically predominate demographic: American women. They want to change the gender balance to include more men, as well as expanding to more international users.</p>

<p>One of the components of this that Dan and John talked about is that in many ways, they don&rsquo;t really understand exactly why Pinterest is so popular (among women), and so it&rsquo;s very difficult to figure out how to attract more male users. Is it because there isn&rsquo;t enough content that&rsquo;s interesting to a male audience, or is the content there but there just isn&rsquo;t a critical mass of male users?</p>

<p>The other (unrelated) aspect of the Pinterest visit that struck me was their open office layout. Every employee is assigned a small desk as their home. All the desks are out in the open and very close to each other. What this means, especially for programmers who need quiet to concentrate, is that they have to find other places to get real work done. I&rsquo;m skeptical of this approach; it might make collaboration easier occasionally, but as a programmer myself, I think that it would be a death knell for my productivity.</p>

<p>The other company we visited is Strava. Strava makes a service (including a web app and mobile apps for iOS and Android) that allows athletes to track their runs or bike rides. Strava has a social aspect that allows users to compete with themselves and with other users over common routes.</p>

<p>We met with Michael, a co-founder, just-stepped-down CEO, and current president of the board of directors. Michael is an excellent speaker (he used to be a professor&hellip;go figure!) and is clearly passionate about entrepreneurship. He gave a lot of advice, but the piece that resonated most with me was what he said about going to business school (I&rsquo;m sort of applying this to grad school too). He said that if you&rsquo;re interested in starting a company, whatever you do, don&rsquo;t get an MBA. If you do, you&rsquo;ll gain skills and a piece of paper that will make you very desireable to many established companies. More importantly, it will most likely put you in the significant debt. When you graduate with the degree and the debt, going to work for a company that will pay you a safe salary will seem very appealing (and you <em>will</em> be recruited heavily).</p>

<p>Instead, you should just start your company as soon as possible. You can get advice from other people on most aspects, and avoiding the debt incurred in going to business school (or grad school) allows you a lot more options in pursuing your own company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sqwiggle and MSLGroup]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/13/sqiggle-and-mslgroup/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T19:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/13/sqiggle-and-mslgroup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, we had our first meetings here in sunny San Francisco. (Seriously, after not seeing the sun for the entire five days in Seattle, it feels like a religious experience to go out for a bike ride in shorts!)</p>

<p>The first group we visited this morning was the PR firm MSL Group, where we met with Bryan Scanlon. Before going in to this meeting, I knew almost nothing about what a public relations firm really does (besides, you know, public relations).</p>

<p>MSL Group is in the top five global PR firms, so they obviously have some pretty big clients. The biggest client that Bryan works with is PayPal, so it was pretty interesting to get a glimpse into what he and the rest of the MSL Group staff do.</p>

<p>One of the things that stood out to me is when someone asked Bryan what kinds of stuff he does when he starts a new campaign or signs a new client. He said that coming up with cool ideas and PR stunts is relatively easy. The hard part is figuring out what effect a particular action has on the customer. Does it help their brand? Does it (accidentally) portray them in a poor light? Does it do anything at all?</p>

<p>Bryan clearly loves his job, and it really came out in his enthusiasm in talking to us. He says that as a PR exec, he has to really learn to know a customer forward, backwards, everything. He has to completely understand their business, their market, their target audience, their challenges, and their image. What this means is that he gets to do wildly different things all the time, and he is always getting to learn new things. One day, he might be writing a blog post for the PayPal corporate blog, while on another day he could be researching the genealogy services market for Ancestry.com.</p>

<p>We also met with Eric Bieller, co-founder of Sqwiggle. Sqwiggle is a startup that&rsquo;s focused on a telepresence solution that&rsquo;s aimed a businesses that want to support remote workers.</p>

<p>Sqwiggle allows a business to have a &ldquo;room&rdquo; that everyone is connected to during the entire day. Each person is represented by a black-and-white still image from their webcam, updated every ten seconds. This provides an at-a-glance check to see if the user is busy, available, etc. From there, it&rsquo;s a matter of clicking on one or more users in the room to start a quick video chat with them. The aim is to replace the action of stopping by a co-worker&rsquo;s cubicle or office to ask them a quick question.</p>

<p>I was a little skeptical at first, but after seeing some impromptu demos, I think I&rsquo;ve been convinced. At a couple of points during our meeting, one of Eric&rsquo;s co-workers pinged him on Sqwiggle. He just said he was busy (or in one case introduced our group) and moved on. The interaction felt really natural and seamless.</p>

<p>Sqwiggle is doing some pretty sweet stuff technically. Their existing product is based on WebRTC with peer-to-peer connections. That stack supports a call with up to four simultaneous users. (The limitation is bandwidth in a P2P setup &ndash; each user has to have a full video stream to every other user). They are working on a federated server model, where they run infrastructure that allows for a conference with more than four users. That system will be based on a Node.js backend.</p>

<p>It was pretty cool to talk with someone as knowledgeable and passionate as Eric. He gave us a lot of really interesting information on the process of forming a tech startup, getting funding from various sources (including AngelList, something I&rsquo;d read about but didn&rsquo;t know a whole lot about), and how (not) to hire early employees.</p>

<p>Apparently, Sqwiggle might be open to hiring interns&hellip;I might just send them an email!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Today, I saw the future]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/08/today-i-saw-the-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T21:36:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/08/today-i-saw-the-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, we spent most of the day on the Microsoft campus in Redmond, Washington (a short bus ride from downtown Seattle).</p>

<p>The first part of the day was a tour of the Microsoft Envisioning Center. The Envisioning Center is a place where Microsoft can demo technologies that they think will become common in the next 5 &ndash; 10 years.</p>

<p>They have the Envisioning Center divided up into a few different sections, representing the future workspace (i.e. the corporate experience) and a model domestic home.</p>

<p>Probably the most significant change that Microsoft thinks the future will hold is in the proliferation of interoperable touch screens. Our tour guide demoed several scenarios where content on a phone or tablet could be &ldquo;thrown&rdquo; onto a big screen to display to a group or simply to see in a bigger format.</p>

<p>Another cool example was a series of networked digital picture frames scattered throughout the model home. The guide could do things like select a series of photos from a family album and have them rotated throughout the home.</p>

<p>The model kitchen was also really interested. The kitchen had projectors everywhere, allowing recipes to be projected on the the food preparation counter, cooking times projected directly onto the pans as they heat on the stove, and video conference consulting with professional chefs anywhere in the world on a large wall screen.</p>

<p>Microsoft is also making a big push to put Kinect motion sensors everywhere, so that interaction with digital objects becomes really easy. We saw a demo of a virtual potter&rsquo;s wheel: a Kinect was used to quickly scan a pottery flower pot and build a digital model of it. Then that digital model could be virtually reshaped simply by moving your hands in front of the sensor, with the effects showing up on screen.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe everything we saw, but if you want to see some of the stuff in the Envisioning Center, Microsoft has a <a href="http://blogs.technet.com/b/next/archive/2013/03/01/step-inside-the-microsoft-envisioning-center.aspx#.Us40GO5dWoI">video</a> showing some of it.</p>

<p>We also got to meet with Neal Leslie, on the Windows Phone Product Evangelization team. His job is to convince developers to write a version of their apps for Windows Phone. Part of the problem that Windows Phone has faced in competing with Apple&rsquo;s iPhone and phones powered by Google&rsquo;s Android is that in a lot of cases, people choose their platform based on the available apps. Neal said that until recently, for example, the increasingly popular Instagram was only available on iOS and Android. He was directly involved in the process of convincing Facebook (who own Instagram) to write a version of Instagram for Windows Phone.</p>

<p>The third and final person we met with at Microsoft was Dave Maltz. Dave Maltz works in Microsoft Research as an engineer working to develop networking technologies for the next generation of data centers. He gave us a ton of information on how networks are organized and built at a large scale, as well as regaling us with some great stories about mishaps he&rsquo;s witnessed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visiting Amazon]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/07/visiting-amazon/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T13:21:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/07/visiting-amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was the first full day of my January-term trip (Entrepreneurship in Silicon Valley) to the West Coast. We&rsquo;re in Seattle, and this morning we visited Amazon&rsquo;s headquarters.</p>

<p>We met with a guy named Sam. Sam works in the legal operations department, although he isn&rsquo;t a lawyer. We spent about an hour talking with him about what he does, what Amazon does, and how Amazon is looking at the future of its various businesses.</p>

<p>I had a chance to ask Sam about the areas that Amazon is most concerned about in near future (~5 years), and he gave me three issues (with a bonus fourth).</p>

<h4>Privacy and Data Security</h4>

<p>The first was issues of privacy and data security, which is really interesting to me. Amazon obviously has a massive database of user information, including the usual contact and financial information that any e-retailer has, but they also have a vast corpus of information about people&rsquo;s preferences: what they&rsquo;ve bought, when they like to buy, what kinds of stuff they would probably consider buying the future.</p>

<p>Sam used the example of the recent Target breach to show how quickly a brand can be damaged by a security issue. Amazon has yet to have a large-scale data leak, but that doesn&rsquo;t mean that people aren&rsquo;t trying.</p>

<h4>Antitrust</h4>

<p>A second major concern that Amazon has about the future is a big one (hehe): antitrust. As Amazon gets bigger and bigger, and has its fingers in more and more pies, they are concerned that federal regulators will start to take notice. Sam didn&rsquo;t elaborate on what Amazon is doing to mitigate the risk, but it doesn&rsquo;t take much looking to find lots of examples of the results of past antitrust investigations (from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breakup_of_the_Bell_System">break-up of Ma Bell in 1982</a>, to the web-browser choice settlements that Microsoft has faced in Europe, or the FTC-blocked <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attempted_purchase_of_T-Mobile_USA_by_AT%26T">attempted acquisition of T-Mobile by AT&amp;T</a>).</p>

<h4>Brand Image</h4>

<p>Sam also mentioned that brand image was a major concern of Amazon. They specifically don&rsquo;t want to &ldquo;be seen as another Walmart.&rdquo; This really isn&rsquo;t unique, although he tied it strongly to the issue of data security and privacy: a major breach would be devastating to their brand image.</p>

<h4>Labor Relations</h4>

<p>The bonus fourth issue is labor relations. The reason I&rsquo;m saying it&rsquo;s a bonus issue is that Sam mentioned this issue as one he personally thinks will be an area of concern. (In other words, Jeff Bezos probably wouldn&rsquo;t mention it). Basically, Amazon has gotten, and continues to get, a lot of flak over its labor practices.</p>

<p>The aspect of this that I know most about is the concerns over how Amazon treats its hourly employees in its fulfillment warehouses. Called &ldquo;pickers&rdquo;, these employees have to work very long hours in very physically demanding conditions, often for low pay. <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2012/02/mac-mcclelland-free-online-shipping-warehouses-labor">This</a> article is an interesting description of some of these issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Favorite StackOverflow Question Of All Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/08/01/my-favorite-stackoverflow-question-of-all-time/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-01T10:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/08/01/my-favorite-stackoverflow-question-of-all-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The best SO question I&rsquo;ve ever seen: <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4456438/how-can-i-pass-the-string-null-through-wsdl-soap-from-as3-to-coldfusion-web?rq=1">How can I pass the string “Null” through WSDL (SOAP) from AS3 to ColdFusion web service without receiving a “missing parameter error”?</a>.</p>

<p>And of course, the obligatory related XCKD:
<img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/exploits_of_a_mom.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamically Load Content With jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/07/02/dynamically-load-content-with-jquery/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T09:04:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/07/02/dynamically-load-content-with-jquery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is more for my reference than anything else.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been working on a fairly simple static site, based on Twitter&rsquo;s <a href="http://twitter.github.io/bootstrap/">Bootstrap</a> framework. I don&rsquo;t really want to add the complexity of a templating system or anything like that, but as the site has started to grow, maintaining a bunch of static pages has gotten a little unwieldy (yesterday I caught myself copy-pasting the footer div to 6 different files&hellip;yuck!)</p>

<p>The solution? Dynamically load content that&rsquo;s repeated across a lot of pages, using jQuery.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how I did it (I&rsquo;ll use the footer as an example):</p>

<p>First, I put the repeated content into a separate HTML file (<code>footer.html</code>).</p>

<p>Then, on each page I want to have this footer in, I put in an empty div in the place I want the footer to be loaded in:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">&quot;footer&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</span> <span class="c">&lt;!-- footer loaded here --&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>At the end of the document, I use a jQuery function to load the content of the footer into the current page:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;#footer&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">load</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;footer.html&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ajaxSetup</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">async</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">false</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The call to <code>ajaxSetup</code> with the <code>async: false</code> parameter is optional. I put it in there to try and reduce the visual &ldquo;flicker&rdquo; that happens when the content is loaded after the rest of the page. There&rsquo;s still a small delay, but it&rsquo;s not really noticeable. It&rsquo;s also probably not necessary for a normal footer, since it&rsquo;s likely to be &ldquo;below the fold&rdquo; anyway.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IdeaVim: Pycharm, Vim-Style]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/18/jetbrains-pycharm-vim-style/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T11:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/18/jetbrains-pycharm-vim-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Vi (actually Vim) now for about a year as my primary code-editor. I really don&rsquo;t like using a mouse when I can help
it, so the Vi keyboard-centric philosophy has been a pretty nice change to my workflow. I&rsquo;m by no means a Vi expert, but for most
things I&rsquo;m quicker doing it in Vi than a more GUI based text editor. (I will still sometimes use GEdit or Sublime if I&rsquo;m going to
be doing a lot of copy-paste work).</p>

<p>However, I&rsquo;ve kind of missed having an actual IDE. Code completion<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> is nice, as is symbol-based code navigation. I doubt I even need
to mention how nice an integrated debugger is! I used <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/">Jetbrains</a> <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ IDEA</a> as a Java/JavaScript IDE at an internship a year ago, and really fell in love with it. The attention to detail and the level of polish really can&rsquo;t be matched by any of the open source offerings. Since then, I&rsquo;ve also used <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">Jetbrains PyCharm</a> for various school projects. PyCharm has the same core and mostly the same interface as IDEA, but with superb Python support baked right in. (PyCharm also has the same JavaScript, HTML, and CSS support that IDEA does, so it&rsquo;s perfect for web development.)</p>

<p>I just discovered that there is an excellent plugin for PyCharm<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> that adds really, really comprehensive Vi-style editing. <a href="http://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/164">IdeaVim</a> supports a pretty large subset of Vi commands. In fact, in my (admittedly pretty novice) usage of Vi commands, I have yet to run in to anything I can do in Vi that I can&rsquo;t in PyCharm with IdeaVim.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a list of supported features (copied from the docs):</p>

<!-- more -->


<pre><code>Supported:
    - Motion keys
    - Deletion/Changing
    - Insert mode commands
    - Marks
    - Registers
    - Undo/redo
    - Visual mode commands
    - Some Ex commands
    - Some :set options
    - Full Vim regexps for search and search/replace
    - Macros
    - Digraphs
    - Command line and search history
    - Vim web help

Not supported (yet):
    - Key mappings
    - Various less used commands
    - Jump lists
    - Window commands
</code></pre>

<p>Not only does it provide comprehensive Vi editing, it&rsquo;s even under active development by a paid Jetbrains developer. That means that bugs and missing stuff gets fixed in a nice and timely manner (you can see the activity level on the <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/ideavim">GitHub page</a>).</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>Installation is dead easy.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Open the PyCharm settings (<code>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;S&gt;</code>)</p></li>
<li><p>Under <code>IDE Settings</code>, choose <code>Plugins</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Click the button that says <code>Install Jetbrains Plugin...</code></p></li>
<li><p>Type <code>IdeaVim</code> into the search box.</p></li>
<li><p>Double click on the IdeaVim plugin when it shows up.</p></li>
<li><p>You&rsquo;ll be prompted to install it and restart PyCharm.</p></li>
<li><p>That&rsquo;s it!</p></li>
</ol>


<p>You can easily toggle the Vi-style editing using <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;V&gt;</code> or choosing <code>Vim Emulator</code> from the <code>Tools</code> menu.</p>

<p>I know that Vi isn&rsquo;t for everyone. However, if you love Vi but can&rsquo;t live without an IDE, definitely take a look at IdeaVim!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I know there are some Vi plugins that allow various levels of code completion, but all of them have some issues and most are kind of a pain to get working.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It actually supports all of the Jetbrains IDE  based on the IntelliJ platform, including IDEA, PhpStorm and RubyMine.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Encrypt your email with Mailvelope]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/11/encrypt-your-email-with-mailvelope/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T09:20:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/11/encrypt-your-email-with-mailvelope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During last week we&rsquo;ve all heard a lot about the previously secret NSA covert surveillance activies. Through the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_(surveillance_program)">PRISM surveillance program</a>, the NSA has at least some access to a lot of user data from many different Internet services, including Google, Facebook, Microsoft, and others.</p>

<p>In addition to this latest revelation, some already-existing laws have the potential affect the privacy of our Internet communications. For example, the <a href="https://ssd.eff.org/book/export/html/42#node-46">&ldquo;abandoned email&rdquo;</a> provision of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_Communications_Privacy_Act">Electronic Communications Privacy Act</a> (ECPA) allows the U.S. government to access emails that have not been read in the last 180 days without probable cause and a warrant. This includes previously read emails that may have been archived or otherwise stored, even in a still-active email account.</p>

<p>Obviously, this is a little disconcerting; our Internet communication is less significantly less private that we previously thought.</p>

<p>One of the ways that we can try to protect our privacy is by encrypting email communication. I recently discovered a handy plugin for Google Chrome called <a href="http://www.mailvelope.com">Mailvelope</a>. Mailvelope seamlessly integrates with the Gmail web interface to provide an easy way to encrypt and decrypt your emails using the OpenPGP standard. (It also seems to support Yahoo and Outlook.com, although I didn&rsquo;t try it with those providers).</p>

<p>When you compose an email and then encrypt it with Mailvelope, the text of the email is replaced with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ciphertext">ciphertext</a>. This means that even if someone (<em>cough</em> NSA <em>cough</em>) accesses the email from your Gmail account, all they can see is the encrypted message.</p>

<p>When the recipient recieves the email, they will have to decrypt it to see what you sent them. They can either use the Mailvelope plugin also (if they have it installed) or one of many other 3rd-party programs that support OpenPGP messages.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how to set up Mailvelope so that you can send and recieve encrypted emails.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Generate Encryption Keys</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Install the Mailvelope plugin (find it in the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/mailvelope/kajibbejlbohfaggdiogboambcijhkke">Chrome web store</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>Now we have to generate your encryption key. (Mailvelope uses public key encryption, so you encrypt an email to someone with their public key and and they use their private key to decrypt it). Click on the Mailvelope padlock icon (to the right of the Chrome address bar) and choose <code>Options</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Click the <code>Generate Key</code> option on the left side of the options page.</p></li>
<li><p>Enter your full name, your email address, and a passphrase, and then click submit. IMPORTANT: Choose a strong, secure passphrase. You will use this passphrase to unlock your private key so that you can decrypt emails sent to you.</p></li>
<li><p>Click <code>Display Keys</code> on the left side of the options page. This will show the list of keys you have available. At this point, the only key that&rsquo;ll be visible is the key we just generated. Notice the icon that looks like two keys. This means that you have both the public and private keys for this keypair. If the icon is a single key, that means that you only have the public key, allowing you to encrypt an email for someone else to read.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Exchanging Public Keys</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>To send an encrypted email to someone, you&rsquo;re going to need their public key. For them to respond, they will need yours. It&rsquo;s totally safe to send a public key by any means &ndash; in fact,  you should publicize it as much as possible so that it&rsquo;s easy for someone to send you an encrypted email. (If you want to send <em>me</em> an encrypted email, you can find my public key <a href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/08/openpgp-key/">here</a>.)</p></li>
<li><p>To display your public key in Mailvelope, click the <code>Export</code> dropdown menu, and choose <code>Display public key</code>. This is the key you want to share.</p></li>
<li><p>Once you have someone else&rsquo;s public key, click <code>Import Keys</code> in the Mailvelope options page. You can simply paste their key (including the <code>-----BEGIN PGP PUBLIC KEY BLOCK-----</code> and <code>-----END PGP PUBLIC KEY BLOCK-----</code> lines) into the text box and click submit.</p></li>
<li><p>Click <code>Display Keys</code> again. Notice that the new public key has been added.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Send An Encrypted Email</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Now open your Gmail account and begin to compose a new email. You can fill out the recipient&rsquo;s email address and subject (remember not to put any sensitive/private information in the subject; it&rsquo;s not encrypted).</p></li>
<li><p>Click the icon that appears when you mouse over the compose area. It looks like a notepad with a yellow pencil. This will bring up the secure compose window.</p></li>
<li><p>Compose your email. When you have finished writing it, click the yellow padlock button. You will be prompted to choose who to encrypt the email for. The dropdown menu has a list of all the keys you have. Choose the name/email address of the person who&rsquo;s public key you imported earlier, and click the &ldquo;Add&rdquo; button.</p></li>
<li><p>Click <code>Ok</code>. The plaintext email you wrote will be replaced with the encrypted email (starting with the line <code>-----BEGIN PGP MESSAGE----- </code> ).</p></li>
<li><p>Click <code>Transfer</code>. This puts the encrypted message into the Gmail compose window.</p></li>
<li><p>Click send. That&rsquo;s it! You just sent an encrypted email.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Decrypting Recieved Email</h2>

<p>Now, assuming this worked, the person you sent the encrypted email to has responded with another message, this time encrypted with <em>your</em> public key. You will have to use the private key we generated earlier to decrypt it.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Open the encrypted email that was sent to you in the Gmail web interface. When you hover over the contents of the encrypted message, Mailvelope will show a padlock icon hovering over the message text.</p></li>
<li><p>Assuming that the person who sent the email encrypted it with your public key, Mailvelope will prompt you to enter the passsphrase for your private key. This is the passphrase you chose when you generated your keypair.</p></li>
<li><p>Enter your passphrase and click <code>Ok</code>. The decrypted secret message will be displayed. That&rsquo;s it!</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Hopefully you now know how to send and recieve encrypted emails. This obviously won&rsquo;t help with other Internet communications, i.e. via Facebook, Twitter, etc. You&rsquo;ll just have to avoid using those platforms for communications of a&hellip;sensitive nature :).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenPGP Key]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/08/openpgp-key/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T10:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/08/openpgp-key</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is my OpenPGP public key. You can email me at <a href='mailto:i@isaacdontjelindell.com'><a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x69;&#64;&#105;&#x73;&#97;&#x61;&#x63;&#x64;&#x6f;&#110;&#x74;&#x6a;&#101;&#x6c;&#x69;&#x6e;&#100;&#101;&#108;&#x6c;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;">&#105;&#x40;&#105;&#x73;&#97;&#x61;&#99;&#100;&#x6f;&#110;&#x74;&#x6a;&#101;&#108;&#x69;&#x6e;&#100;&#101;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;</a></a>.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>-----BEGIN PGP PUBLIC KEY BLOCK-----
</span><span class='line'>Version: OpenPGP.js v.1.20130228
</span><span class='line'>Comment: http://openpgpjs.org
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>xsBNBFG8ib4BCACS1m8aLM+aQlpo/HHEmHWXEzR3Pb9O0acAT7qR3C0+JutA
</span><span class='line'>1VTrK0onZc7I5LdmxWIJ4pXYUm/PR6lZOI4srhTkjBmHEzIOia5hpAqE18ML
</span><span class='line'>nR+3coYFqFE+ALBIO3VpmmUuOGB6V18sqvUrX/JdsvMXwbu+IkAAPnkgos5M
</span><span class='line'>qmBA62nOZwDU2PA/NRdYZJcWqurBvs7lzdkfV4im3lh1b5cZnhym9NcJFs5a
</span><span class='line'>J/lyLjhQd+OYKp9EZlq4ETfua/EcQRh1AKPo+dx+q0jG/wpMkzjrAwKo6cC9
</span><span class='line'>cMx3nXsJfhnsChnnU3LzLFjNCINITLfgbK9cGR+mYXDxI6QKQntX+MAfABEB
</span><span class='line'>AAHNL0lzYWFjIERvbnRqZSBMaW5kZWxsIDxpQGlzYWFjZG9udGplbGluZGVs
</span><span class='line'>bC5jb20+wsBcBBABAgAQBQJRvInDCRCtoDOA/EbfYQAAzjMH/0fZPo82U3+k
</span><span class='line'>wS+UCt3wTNlOUYxULzGewjg6A6bx8dJpGPJG7fL7Vw+ltpOnvkWfUdlcgvl4
</span><span class='line'>S5hGdxluLhQ5X7coP/Hsy9Py8vGF3DYh1fDUPrJOt0tjR7ksjo56DSVagqqr
</span><span class='line'>7+3wd49kvXjBH7djKj319SZByR+99AopWvqxyrViBSZCSbO33JDBZkFqdewi
</span><span class='line'>XWx4gGOQ7e97VhCAx46k6oA7xZOcTSFhpa8MuuuxCe05VtyYdlmbiU/zogWZ
</span><span class='line'>/cw1L23x7As0OaQ3dMIujnXUK2viuoOsfasQHtXc3HVsz32drSCXxSi8o+eU
</span><span class='line'>sEdyphgKp+WcWTsbKkXqoITWckCmbiM=
</span><span class='line'>=QEOg
</span><span class='line'>-----END PGP PUBLIC KEY BLOCK-----</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multiple Ubuntu Unity Sessions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/08/ubuntu-multiple-sessions/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T09:20:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2013/06/08/ubuntu-multiple-sessions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often find myself working on several programming projects at once. This generally involves one or more Chrome windows, multiple Vi terminal windows, and miscellaneous text editors, Gimp windows, Evernote pages, etc, all arranged over multiple workspaces (usually the same ones so I can find stuff quickly!).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve often wished I could have multiple X sessions running at the same time, completely independent of each other. Then I could have one project open and spread out, while being able to quickly switch to a different project, with its unique set of windows and layout options.</p>

<p>I just discovered that if multiple users are logged in to an Ubuntu machine, it&rsquo;ll put each user&rsquo;s X session in a separate TTY (virtual terminal). The first 6, TTY1 &ndash; TTY6, are console sessions. The first user to log into a graphical session in Ubuntu is on TTY7. If you switch users (Gear menu &ndash;> Switch Users) and log in to a different user account on the computer, it will start that session on TTY8.</p>

<p>Note: TTY&rsquo;s can be accessed by typing <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;tty_num %F%&gt;</code>. So to access TTY8, for example, I would type <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;F8&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>I had originally hoped that I could start a separate X session but still log in as my main user account. Unfortuantely, this doesn&rsquo;t seem to be possible with Unity &ndash; I can start another X session and log in, and even manually start Unity, but every time I open programs, they appear in the first Unity session, on TTY7.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As a workaround, I created another user account so that I can start another session. It&rsquo;s kind of a hack, because the second user obviously doesn&rsquo;t have access to all the customizations, files, etc. Since a large portion of my work is at the terminal anyway, I can just run <code>sudo su &lt;main_user_account&gt;</code> and impersonate my main user account from the second one.</p>

<p>As far as other customizations, it&rsquo;ll probably take a little to get them all there (wobbly windows, anyone?) but I think it&rsquo;s worth it. I&rsquo;m already pretty attached to being able to <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;&lt;alt&gt;&lt;f8&gt;</code> and instantly switch to a completely different project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
