<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jterm | technicall]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/categories/jterm/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-19T22:51:40-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Isaac Dontje Lindell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assimilation into the GooglePlex]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/assimilation-into-the-googleplex/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T09:26:02-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/18/assimilation-into-the-googleplex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, we visited Google headquarters, in Mountain View, California. It was certainly an impressive experience, but I was left with some mixed feelings about the experience.</p>

<p>First of all, Google is obviously doing some really cool stuff. My computer and Internet experience would be very different without Google. I use Gmail, Calendar, Maps, Search, Chrome, and other products every day. Large parts of the Internet are financed by Google-served ads.</p>

<p>Google also has the deep pockets and corporate will to perform groundbreaking research. Their self-driving car is incredible, and Google Glass is pretty revolutionary (whatever you think about the benefit to humanity).</p>

<p>On the other hand, I found myself fairly uncomfortable at many points during our visit yesterday. One of the people we met was Craig Cornelius, a former Luther alumna who works on the internationalization team (i18n) at Google. One of the first things Craig said when he starting talking about Google was, &ldquo;how much do you pay Google to use our services?&rdquo; It&rsquo;s a fairly innocuous question, but he clearly expected us to answer that we paid nothing.</p>

<p>When someone said that we paid with our personal information, he sort of acknowledged the point, but then immediately moved on to convincing us that because we don&rsquo;t &ldquo;cut Google a check,&rdquo; we really aren&rsquo;t paying anything. That unwillingness to acknowledge Google&rsquo;s core money-maker (our data) leaves a bad taste in my mouth.</p>

<p>I give them that data willingly, in exchange for some very useful services and products. But if Craig&rsquo;s perspective is common at Google, I have to feel like they&rsquo;re simply trying to forget (or convince the rest of us to forget) that we <em>are</em> paying them.</p>

<p>I did enjoying seeing the campus with Charles Banta (a recent Luther grad, and someone I&rsquo;ve worked with at the Luther Tech Help Desk), and getting to see some of the perks that Googlers get. Google clearly views time that employees are not on campus as wasted time. And when you can eat, drink, sleep, get a haircut, get your car repaired, do your laundry, see a doctor, and work out on campus, what&rsquo;s the point of going home?</p>

<p>Again, it would be fun to work at Google, and I know that Charles is really enjoying it. But I can&rsquo;t help but think that your life would quickly become Google-centric. It&rsquo;s one thing to love your job and want to work a lot (a situation I hope to find myself in when I enter the job market), but the word &ldquo;assimilation&rdquo; kept popping in to my head during the entire visit. (For a fictional take on this, I highly recommend reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18302455-the-circle">The Circle</a> by Dave Eggers. Just replace &ldquo;The Circle&rdquo; with &ldquo;Google&rdquo; and you&rsquo;ll have a good idea how I felt visting Google.)</p>

<p>Two of the technical talks we heard, however, were fantastic. Craig Cornelius gave a lecture on the challenges of internationalization of Google products. It didn&rsquo;t sound that interesting at first, but his team has to solve so incredibly difficult projects. How you design projects so that they work equally well with left-to-right AND right-to-left languages? How do you handle keyboard input in a language that has thousands of &ldquo;letters&rdquo;? How do you deal with one of the hundreds of ways a single date and time can be expressed?</p>

<p>We also had a chance to hear a little bit from Brian, an engineer on Google&rsquo;s self-driving car team (unfortunately, I didn&rsquo;t manage to catch his last name). We didn&rsquo;t have a chance to get as technical as I would have liked due to time issues, but he had a great introduction to the technology behind the &ldquo;perception suite&rdquo; that&rsquo;s used to make the car &ldquo;see&rdquo;, and some interesting scenarios for possible societal changes that might be caused by the introduction of autonomous cars.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Future of Software: Venture Capitalists vs. Scientists]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/16/hummer-winblad-and-phillip-alvelda/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T23:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/16/hummer-winblad-and-phillip-alvelda</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was our last day here in San Francisco. Tomorrow morning, we&rsquo;re getting on a shuttle down to Palo Alto/Mountain View and the GooglePlex!</p>

<p>This morning, we met with Ann Winblad, of Hummer Winblad Venture Partners. (Ann&rsquo;s VC firm was one of the early funders of Brad&rsquo;s startup, NetPerceptions). Ann is an incredibly engaging speaker, and she gave us a great intro to the world of venture capital, and a lot of description of where she thinks the world of commercial software development is going.</p>

<p>One of Ann&rsquo;s main points is that software development is no longer a task where an isolated startup or other company will write a product from the ground up. Instead, software development comes down to connecting existing components together, leveraging existing corpora of data or databases of prepackaged software components (e.g. Maven).</p>

<p>I found myself thinking about this a lot, and I&rsquo;m still not sure if I totally agree. It&rsquo;s very true that it&rsquo;s easy to build cool pieces of software simply by leveraging other existing software. For example, I&rsquo;m working on a web application that&rsquo;s a prettier, friendlier front end to the Calibre ebook management software. I&rsquo;m (obviously) using the interface exposed by Calibre to get book metadata. I&rsquo;m using Bootstrap to lay out the interface (a designer I am not!). I&rsquo;m using a framework called Angular.js to handle displaying data and updating it easily.</p>

<p>On the other hand, doing this still requires a fair amount of &ldquo;glue&rdquo; code. I have to design a user flow. I have to make sure the right data is shown at the right time. Even with Bootstrap, I have to make at least some effort to make sure it looks decent.</p>

<p>Another perspective on this came from Phillip Alvelda, a serial entrepreneur and scientist, whom we also met with today. Phillip&rsquo;s counterpoint when I mentioned what Ann had talked about was that I should take anything said by a venture capitalist with a grain of salt. They aim to find investments that are low risk and have a very high potential payoff. Designing software that builds on already existing software takes less time and programmer skill (i.e. lower risk) and consequently has a better chance of &ldquo;getting big.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Phillip&rsquo;s point is that while the type of development Ann favored is a quick way to make money, it&rsquo;s not a good way to truly innovate. Things that require scientific research, or hardware investment, or both, are risky and expensive. While they often have a chance at a huge payoff, venture capitalists are very hesitant to fund such ventures. (Phillip gave the specific example of Elon Musk&rsquo;s now-abandoned hyperloop idea: it had the potential to be extremely innovative, but was expensive and very risky).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also taking what Phillip said about VCs (and Ann Winblad specifically) with a small grain of salt: he mentioned that he&rsquo;s asked Hummer Winblad for investment for three different ventures, and has been turned down all three times&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bizo, MoovWeb, and Sara Ellefsen]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/15/bizo/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T19:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/15/bizo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was a really long day! We visited three groups, all doing very different things.</p>

<p>This morning, we met with a company called Bizo. Bizo does B2B (business to business) Internet marketing. Their customers are other businesses who want to run advertising campaigns on the Internet. They had some interesting perspectives on their business, which is in many ways bigger than a startup but still a pretty small company, but the most interesting part of the conversation for me was in the interview and career advice they had near the end of our visit.</p>

<p>They emphasized that when they interview people, one of their primary concerns (beyond a minimum technical bar) is that the candidate matches their culture. I heard over and over, &ldquo;is this [candidate] someone I would enjoy working with?&rdquo; I couldn&rsquo;t help but draw comparisons to the way that Matt at VMWare talked about hiring. He was much more concerned about technical ability and problem solving; he said several times that he wanted to work with &ldquo;the smartest people in the world.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Brad (our professor) had an interesting perspective on that: the people at Bizo are doing interesting things, but they aren&rsquo;t doing revolutionary or innovative computer science. They&rsquo;re just &ldquo;pushing bits around&rdquo;. On the other hand, VMWare is obviously tackling some very difficult engineering problems. The ablilty of the candidate is much more important than their &ldquo;culture fit.&rdquo;</p>

<p>We met with some developers from a company called MoovWeb for lunch. MoovWeb&rsquo;s service is one that allows businesses that have an existing complicated desktop web site to convert it to a mobile-friendly version with much less effort than simply re-writing the whole site. It was fun to get a chance to have some informal and in-depth technical discussions with the developers. They&rsquo;re doing some cool stuff with dynamically regenerating sites using a server side architecture (written in Go, no less!)</p>

<p>The last meeting of the day was with a personal finance planner, Sara Ellefsen. Sara works with mostly individuals and families to help them plan and manage their investment portfolio. As a broke college student, it&rsquo;s difficult for me to think about investing and financial planning, but she had some really good advice for how to approach saving and investing, and it was intriguing to see her approach to risk management.</p>

<p>Sara is certainly a (successful) entrepreneur, but of a very different philosophy than many of the startups we&rsquo;ve been meeting with. She doesn&rsquo;t have any employees, and isn&rsquo;t particularly interested in expanding. She likes what she does, and doesn&rsquo;t have grand visions of making millions and starting a global empire.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pinterest and Strava]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/14/pinterest-and-strava/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T20:59:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/14/pinterest-and-strava</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, day 9, we visited Pinterest and Strava.</p>

<p>The first visit was to the Pinterest headquarters in the Soma neighborhood of San Francisco. (If you aren&rsquo;t familiar with Pinterest, it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;social pinning&rdquo; site where users can pin pictures, links, and notes about stuff that interests them on virtual bulletin boards.)</p>

<p>We had a chance to meet with John and Dan, two data scientists at Pinterest. As data scientists, they&rsquo;re responsible for analyzing metrics related to the service that Pinterest provides, and making sure that issues are resolved. On a technical basis, that means using things like the R programming language, the Hadoop database engine, and various other analytic tools to measure metrics from user engagement to site reliability to demographic information.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting challenges that Pinterest is facing is how to expand its user base from their historically predominate demographic: American women. They want to change the gender balance to include more men, as well as expanding to more international users.</p>

<p>One of the components of this that Dan and John talked about is that in many ways, they don&rsquo;t really understand exactly why Pinterest is so popular (among women), and so it&rsquo;s very difficult to figure out how to attract more male users. Is it because there isn&rsquo;t enough content that&rsquo;s interesting to a male audience, or is the content there but there just isn&rsquo;t a critical mass of male users?</p>

<p>The other (unrelated) aspect of the Pinterest visit that struck me was their open office layout. Every employee is assigned a small desk as their home. All the desks are out in the open and very close to each other. What this means, especially for programmers who need quiet to concentrate, is that they have to find other places to get real work done. I&rsquo;m skeptical of this approach; it might make collaboration easier occasionally, but as a programmer myself, I think that it would be a death knell for my productivity.</p>

<p>The other company we visited is Strava. Strava makes a service (including a web app and mobile apps for iOS and Android) that allows athletes to track their runs or bike rides. Strava has a social aspect that allows users to compete with themselves and with other users over common routes.</p>

<p>We met with Michael, a co-founder, just-stepped-down CEO, and current president of the board of directors. Michael is an excellent speaker (he used to be a professor&hellip;go figure!) and is clearly passionate about entrepreneurship. He gave a lot of advice, but the piece that resonated most with me was what he said about going to business school (I&rsquo;m sort of applying this to grad school too). He said that if you&rsquo;re interested in starting a company, whatever you do, don&rsquo;t get an MBA. If you do, you&rsquo;ll gain skills and a piece of paper that will make you very desireable to many established companies. More importantly, it will most likely put you in the significant debt. When you graduate with the degree and the debt, going to work for a company that will pay you a safe salary will seem very appealing (and you <em>will</em> be recruited heavily).</p>

<p>Instead, you should just start your company as soon as possible. You can get advice from other people on most aspects, and avoiding the debt incurred in going to business school (or grad school) allows you a lot more options in pursuing your own company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sqwiggle and MSLGroup]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/13/sqiggle-and-mslgroup/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T19:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.isaacdontjelindell.com/blog/2014/01/13/sqiggle-and-mslgroup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, we had our first meetings here in sunny San Francisco. (Seriously, after not seeing the sun for the entire five days in Seattle, it feels like a religious experience to go out for a bike ride in shorts!)</p>

<p>The first group we visited this morning was the PR firm MSL Group, where we met with Bryan Scanlon. Before going in to this meeting, I knew almost nothing about what a public relations firm really does (besides, you know, public relations).</p>

<p>MSL Group is in the top five global PR firms, so they obviously have some pretty big clients. The biggest client that Bryan works with is PayPal, so it was pretty interesting to get a glimpse into what he and the rest of the MSL Group staff do.</p>

<p>One of the things that stood out to me is when someone asked Bryan what kinds of stuff he does when he starts a new campaign or signs a new client. He said that coming up with cool ideas and PR stunts is relatively easy. The hard part is figuring out what effect a particular action has on the customer. Does it help their brand? Does it (accidentally) portray them in a poor light? Does it do anything at all?</p>

<p>Bryan clearly loves his job, and it really came out in his enthusiasm in talking to us. He says that as a PR exec, he has to really learn to know a customer forward, backwards, everything. He has to completely understand their business, their market, their target audience, their challenges, and their image. What this means is that he gets to do wildly different things all the time, and he is always getting to learn new things. One day, he might be writing a blog post for the PayPal corporate blog, while on another day he could be researching the genealogy services market for Ancestry.com.</p>

<p>We also met with Eric Bieller, co-founder of Sqwiggle. Sqwiggle is a startup that&rsquo;s focused on a telepresence solution that&rsquo;s aimed a businesses that want to support remote workers.</p>

<p>Sqwiggle allows a business to have a &ldquo;room&rdquo; that everyone is connected to during the entire day. Each person is represented by a black-and-white still image from their webcam, updated every ten seconds. This provides an at-a-glance check to see if the user is busy, available, etc. From there, it&rsquo;s a matter of clicking on one or more users in the room to start a quick video chat with them. The aim is to replace the action of stopping by a co-worker&rsquo;s cubicle or office to ask them a quick question.</p>

<p>I was a little skeptical at first, but after seeing some impromptu demos, I think I&rsquo;ve been convinced. At a couple of points during our meeting, one of Eric&rsquo;s co-workers pinged him on Sqwiggle. He just said he was busy (or in one case introduced our group) and moved on. The interaction felt really natural and seamless.</p>

<p>Sqwiggle is doing some pretty sweet stuff technically. Their existing product is based on WebRTC with peer-to-peer connections. That stack supports a call with up to four simultaneous users. (The limitation is bandwidth in a P2P setup &ndash; each user has to have a full video stream to every other user). They are working on a federated server model, where they run infrastructure that allows for a conference with more than four users. That system will be based on a Node.js backend.</p>

<p>It was pretty cool to talk with someone as knowledgeable and passionate as Eric. He gave us a lot of really interesting information on the process of forming a tech startup, getting funding from various sources (including AngelList, something I&rsquo;d read about but didn&rsquo;t know a whole lot about), and how (not) to hire early employees.</p>

<p>Apparently, Sqwiggle might be open to hiring interns&hellip;I might just send them an email!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
